Abandoned artificial satellites.
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
（ナレーション）
使い捨てられた人工衛星
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
This vast amount of junk floating in space,
space debris, is a very serious threat.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
宇宙に浮かぶ たくさんのゴミ
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 実[じつ, じち]:truth|sincerity|content|, 実[み]:fruit|seed|(in broth) pieces of meat, vegetable, etc.|, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
スペースデブリは
実は とても危険な存在です
This is a story of 2075, a time in which
this space garbage has become a problem.
2075年―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは 宇宙のゴミが
問題になった時代の物語
♪～
時空[じくう]:space-time, 越える[こえる]:to cross over/to cross|to exceed, 夢を見る[ゆめをみる]:to dream/to have a dream
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
静寂[せいじゃく, しじま]:silence/stillness/quietness, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 抱く[いだく, だく]:to embrace|to harbour (e.g. grudge)|to have sex with|
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
鳥[とり]:bird|bird meat (esp. chicken meat)/fowl, 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
儚い[はかない]:fleeting/transient|empty (dream, etc.), 生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
幾[いく]:some|many|how many?, 幾[ほとほと]:quite (usu. negative connotation)/utterly/really, 千[せん, ち]:1,000/thousand, 朝[あさ, あした]:morning, 朝[ちょう]:dynasty|reign|period||
♪幾千の朝に
光[ひかり]:light|illumination|happiness||, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
♪光が向かう場所へ
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
羽ばたく[はばたく]:to flap (wings)|to spread one's wings/to go out into the world
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
願い[ねがい]:desire/wish/request, 放つ[はなつ]:to fire (gun, arrow, questions, etc.)|to set free|to emit (e.g. light)||
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 乗せる[のせる]:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride|to load (luggage)||
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
フロンティア:frontier
♪フロンティアへ
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
Phase 3
Return Trajectory
うーん:hmm/well, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
（タナベ）うーん… 先輩
ここ どう書けばいいんですか？
Senpai, what should I write here?
（ハチマキ）
なんで俺に聞くんだよ
What are you
asking me for?
始末書[しまつしょ]:written explanation or apology, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, いちばん:number one/first|best, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
始末書なら 先輩がいちばん
たくさん書いてるからって皆さんが
Everybody says that you've sent in more written
apologies than anyone else, so I thought...
皆[みんな, みな]:all/everyone|everything
（ハチマキ）んあ？ 皆さん？
They did, huh?
Senpai...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
先輩
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light), 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
分かった
じゃ 言うとおりに書けよ
Yeah, fine.
Write down what I say.
Sure.
はい
"Sorry about nearly screwing up
your flight."
定期便[ていきびん]:regular service, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
“定期便の邪魔をして悪かったな”
"But we might end up doing it again,
so bear with us, okay?"
やらかす:to fail/to blunder|to drink up, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
“けど また やらかしちまうかも
しれないから よろしくな”
Senpai, you'll never be popular
with the girls with that attitude.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, モテる:to be popular (esp. with the opposite sex)/to be well liked/to be pampered (spoiled, doted upon, etc.)
先輩 そんなんじゃ
女の子にモテませんよ
Nobody asked you. The girls with
an eye for quality are lookin'.
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, お世話[おせわ]:help/aid/assistance, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly
余計なお世話だ
見てる女は ちゃんと見てるんだよ
They go, "I've had my eye
on you for ages!"
ずっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)/throughout|much (better, etc.)
ずっと あなたを見てました
"I've worried myself sick with you
working such a dangerous job!"
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, たまる:to collect/to gather/to save, たまる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
危険な仕事をするあなたのことが
心配でたまらないんです… ってな
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship
マイ宇宙船のときも
そうでしたけど―
It was like this during the
"my spaceship" incident, too.
漫画[まんが, マンガ]:cartoon/comic/comic strip, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 発想[はっそう]:idea/conception|expression
どうして
そう 漫画みたいな発想しか―
Why are all of your fantasies like
something out of a comic book?
出てこないんですか？
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
お前なあ 新入りのくせに
少しは先輩を…
Look here, rookie! How about showing
your senpai a little...
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
お前なあ 新入りのくせに
少しは先輩を…
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
（女性）こんにちは
星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)さん
- Hello there, Hoshino Hachirota-san!
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
（女性）こんにちは
星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)さん
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
（女性）こんにちは
星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)さん
あっ…
Um... And you are...?
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ..., どちら:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives)
（ハチマキ）
えーっと どちらさまでしょうか？
ずーっと:continuously in some state (for a long time, distance)|much (better, etc.)|far away|
（女性）
ずーっと見ていたわ あなたのこと
I've had my eye on you
for ages.
えっ…
危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
危険な仕事をしている
あなたのことが―
I worry myself sick with you
working such a dangerous job.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, たまる:to collect/to gather/to save, たまる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
心配でたまらないの
ああ…
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
（女性）あなたのこと もっと
いろいろと教えてほしいの
There are so many things I want
you to tell me about yourself.
S-Sure, if there's anything
I can do to help...
（ハチマキ）はい 僕で よければ…
Then, would you mind
signing this?
サイン:autograph/signature
じゃあ これにサインして！
（ハチマキ）あ？
You mustn't let your guard down
just because you're young!
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number), 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
（女性）
若いからって 安心してちゃ駄目よ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full
宇宙には危険がいっぱい
Outer space
is full of dangers!
いざというとき:when it's important/when it comes to the crunch/when push comes to shove, コズミック:cosmic, 生命保険[せいめいほけん]:life insurance
いざというときの
コズミック生命保険 ね？
Cosmic Life Insurance is there
for life's little surprises. Right?
Insurance?
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee
保険？
（ハチマキ）くっ 出てけーっ！
GET OUT!
恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（女性）もう
恥ずかしがり屋さんなんだから～
Oh, I love how you play
hard to get!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 勧誘[かんゆう]:invitation/solicitation/canvassing, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
保険の勧誘って
宇宙にもあるんですね
Wow, there's insurance solicitation
even in space...
Especially at this time
of year.
特に[とくに]:particularly/especially, 時期[じき]:time/season|soon
（フィー）特に この時期はね
時期[じき]:time/season|soon
この時期？
This time of year?
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally
（保険外交員１）
事故は もちろん―
Accidents are covered, naturally, as are
all of your family's medical expenses!
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 病気[びょうき]:illness/disease/sickness, 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, カバー:cover/covering/dust jacket
ご家族の病気も
全てカバーするんですよ
I already have insurance.
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee
（課長）
保険なら もう 入ってるから
That's not true
at all, sir!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
（保険外交員２）
いえいえ それが大間違い
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 従来[じゅうらい]:up to now/so far|traditional, 異なる[ことなる]:to differ/to vary/to disagree, タイプ:type/kind/sort
私どもの保険は
従来のものとは異なるタイプでして
My company's insurance is unlike
any insurance that's come before!
毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, 同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
（ラビィ）そう言って
毎年 同じやつじゃないか
- Can I have one?
They say that, but it's the same old thing every year.
- Have them all if you like.
- In that case...
Hachi, this one's yours.
さあ ハチ これ お前の分
面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care
たく… 面倒くせえなあ
Man, what a pain
in the ass...
Just use the one I turned in
last year.
去年[きょねん, こぞ]:last year
去年のやつ そのまま使ってくれよ
Company policy is that you
make a new one every year.
毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, 新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 決まり[きまり]:rule|settlement|habit||
毎年 新しく書くのが
決まりなんだから
はい タナベ君も
And one for you, Tanabe-kun.
何ですか？ これ
What's this for?
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
遺言状だよ
（タナベ）えっ？
Your last will
and testament.
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 封筒[ふうとう]:envelope, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, シール:seal, 貼る[はる]:to stick|to stretch|to form (e.g. ice on a pond)||, 提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation
書いたら この封筒に入れて
シール 貼って提出
Once you've written it, put it in
the envelope, seal it, and turn it in.
締め切り[しめきり]:deadline|cofferdam|closed (door, window, etc.), 今週[こんしゅう]:this week
締め切りは 今週中だから
The deadline is the end
of the week, okay?
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
遺言状？
Last will
and testament?
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
ちょっ それって
死ぬとき書く あれですよね？
W-Wait, you mean that thing
you write for when you die?!
そうだよ
That's right.
In this job, there's no telling
when you might die.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
この仕事は
いつ死ぬか分かんねえからな
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
（フィー）
実際 この間も死にかけたしね
Yeah, you almost died
a while back, remember?
あっ…
（タナベ）そんな…
You're kidding...
That's right! Life insurance is for those
"You're kidding" times in life.
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman
（保険外交員１）そうなんですよ
生命保険[せいめいほけん]:life insurance, 保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice
そんな もしものための生命保険
（保険外交員２）備えて安心―
Preparedness is peace of mind.
Satisfaction once you're signed up.
満足[まんぞく]:satisfaction/contentment|sufficient, 税金[ぜいきん]:tax/duty, 安い[やすい]:cheap/inexpensive|calm
入って満足
税金も お安くなりますし
And it lowers
your tax bill, too.
Um, what should I do
about insurance?
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee
あの… 保険って どうすれば
好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to), 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 時期[じき]:time/season|soon
好きにしたら
遺言状の時期って―
It's your call.
"Will Season" is when they
make their money,
so I'm sure they'll be happy
to tell you all about it.
稼ぎ時[かせぎどき]:winning streak/good time to make a profit, いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
彼らも稼ぎ時だから
いっぱい教えてもらえるしね
機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity, 死後[しご]:after death, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
いい機会だから 死後のこととか
いろいろ考えてみてもいいかもよ
It's also a good opportunity to give some thought
to what'll happen after you die
and stuff like that.
（タナベ）はあ
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（保険外交員１）
保険屋のクズだ クズ
You give insurance salesmen
a bad name!
保険会社[ほけんがいしゃ]:insurance company, 方々[かたがた]:they (of people)|you (usu. plural)|various, 方々[ほうぼう]:here and there/this way and that way/everywhere, 必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 受け付け[うけつけ]:reception (desk)/information desk|receipt, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（係員）保険会社の方々は
必ず受け付けを済ませてください
All insurance company personnel,
please make sure to register with reception.
許可証[きょかしょう]:permit/license/licence, 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 管轄[かんかつ]:jurisdiction/control, かぎり:limit/limits|degree
許可証は テクノーラ社の
管轄であるかぎりは―
Permits are valid for all one-G and zero-G blocks,
so long as they are under Technora jurisdiction.
および:and/as well as, および:finger/toe/digit, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way), 全て[すべて]:everything/all|entirely, 有効[ゆうこう]:valid/effective|yuko (judo)
１Ｇおよび ０Ｇブロック
全て有効です
A small premium will give you
lifelong coverage!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, わずか:only/merely/(a) little, 掛け金[かけきん]:installment/instalment/premium, 掛け金[かけがね]:latch/lock|joint of the jaw, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 保障[ほしょう]:guarantee/security/assurance
（保険外交員１）
わずかの掛け金で一生保障
老後[ろうご]:old age, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice
これで老後も安心ですよ
It'll give you peace of mind
in your golden years!
You'll recoup your investment
once it reaches maturity,
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 満期[まんき]:expiration (of a term)/maturity (e.g. investment), 戻ってくる[もどってくる]:to come back
（保険外交員２）
満期になれば戻ってくるんだし―
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number)
こういうのは
若いうちに入っといたほうが―
...so you get the best deal by signing up
for these things while you're still young!
得[とく]:profit/advantage|rebirth in paradise, entering nirvana, 得[う]:to get/to acquire|to be possible
何かとお得なんだから
あら あなたは どう？
Oh, and how about you,
young man?
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc.
（男性）いや 僕はベガ社なんで…
No thanks.
I'm with Vega Corp, so l...
Oh! I'll see you
next month, then!
来月[らいげつ]:next month, よろしく:well/properly|best regards
あら じゃあ 来月よろしくね
Please, for heaven's sake!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 頼む[たのむ]:to request|to call|to entrust to|, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
（保険外交員１）
頼みますよ 助けると思って
My company is rated triple-A,
so choose mine!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 格付け[かくづけ, かくずけ]:rating/classification/allocation, トリプル:triple
（保険外交員２）我が社は
格付けトリプルＡですから
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, か月[かげつ]:months (period of)
（保険外交員３）
３か月だけ ３か月だけでいいから
Three months! Just for three months!
I'll give you all the little gifts I have!
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair), 粗品[そしな, そひん]:inferior goods|trifling gift|gift given out by companies to customers as a token of gratitude
全部あげる この粗品
か月[かげつ]:months (period of), ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（チェンシン）えっ でも まあ
３か月ぐらいなら…
Well, if it's just three
months, maybe I could...
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（保険外交員３）ありがとう！
Thank you!
苦しい[くるしい]:painful|needy|forced (smile, joke)||
く… 苦しい
C-Can't breathe...!
I'm sorry!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman
すいませーん
（保険外交員４）ああ 待って
Hey, wait!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, ノルマ:(one's) quota/assignment
（保険外交員５）
ノルマがあるのよ ノルマが
But I have a quota to meet!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks
（保険外交員３）ありがとう
- Thank you so much!
今年[ことし, こんねん]:this year, やっかい:trouble/burden|care, やっかい:translating and explaining, 季節[きせつ]:season
（ラビィ）今年も やっかいな
季節がやってきましたねえ
The most annoying season of the year
is upon us once again, isn't it, Chief?
When you listen to those agents give their spiel,
you end up signing something somehow.
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 説明[せつめい]:explanation/exposition
（課長）
保険屋さんの説明 聞いてると―
なんか入っちゃうんだよねえ
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ラビィ）
私ら デブリ課といっても―
We're in Debris Section,
but we mostly do desk work...
デスクワーク:desk work
デスクワークですしね
I'm about ready to retire, so I don't need
insurance that costs that much...
定年[ていねん]:retirement age|years of service in a military rank before eligibility for promotion
僕 もうすぐ 定年だからさ―
高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
そんなに高い保険なんか
入らなくてもいいんだけど
グッドアイデア:good, グッドアイデア:idea, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 名付ける[なづける]:to name/to call/to christen
グッドアイデアがありますよ
課長 名付けて―
I have got a great idea, Chief!
I call it...
グッドアイデア:good, グッドアイデア:idea, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 名付ける[なづける]:to name/to call/to christen
グッドアイデアがありますよ
課長 名付けて―
（課長）あ？
..."Operation See no Evil,
Speak no Evil, Hear no Evil."
（課長）あ？
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations
“見ざる 言わざる
聞かざる作戦”ですよ
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations
“見ざる 言わざる
聞かざる作戦”ですよ
作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations
“見ざる 言わざる
聞かざる作戦”ですよ
（課長）ああ
勧誘[かんゆう]:invitation/solicitation/canvassing, しよう:way/method|(technical) specification, しよう:use/application/employment
これなら
勧誘のしようが ないでしょ？
（課長）ああ
If we do that, they can't
sell us anything, right?
Hey, that's
a good idea!
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
ああ そりゃ いいねえ
Isn't it, though? I was up all
last night coming up with it.
ゆうべ:evening|last night, 寝る[ねる]:to lie down|to go to bed|to sleep (lying down)||, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
でしょ！
ゆうべ寝ないで考えましたから
（課長）
うわっ ラビィちゃん 下 下
Lavie! Look down!
Look down!
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse
あっ 申し訳ありません
I'm so sorry!
Forget about that,
just put that back!
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price)
いいから 早く戻して
（ラビィ）あっ はい
Yes, sir!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 先立つ[さきだつ]:to lead|to precede|to die before (esp. one's spouse, parents, etc.)|, 不孝[ふこう, ふきょう]:undutifulness to one's parents|(the crime of) cursing one's parents|disowning one's child, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）“お父さん お母さん
先立つ不孝をお許しください”
"Dear Mom and Dad, please forgive the sadness
I've caused by dying before you."
うーん:hmm/well, お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa
うーん… “お父さんへ”
"Dear Dad. Rock music doesn't
work with funerals, so don't..."
葬式[そうしき]:funeral, ロック:lock, 似合う[にあう]:to suit/to match/to become
“葬式にロックは
似合わないので”って 違う
No, that's no good...
"Write out your last will,"
they say...
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden
遺言なんて
いきなり言われてもなあ
ん？
あっ 何？ これ
What's this?
Hey.
（ハチマキ）おい
あっ
Who said you could
look at that?
勝手に[かってに]:arbitrarily/of its own accord/voluntarily
何 勝手に見てんだよ
あっ その 何ですか？ これ
I was just, uh...
What is this?
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request
（ハチマキ）遺言
My last will.
えっ はあ？
You were told to write one, too, remember?
They said to turn it in by the end of the week.
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 今週[こんしゅう]:this week, 出す[だす]:to take out|to put out|to submit (e.g. thesis)||
お前も書けって言われたろ？
今週中に出せって
Your last will? Seriously?
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, ほんと:truth/reality|proper
遺言 ほんとに？
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
何だよ 何か文句でもあるのか？
What, you got a problem with that
or something?
But a will is supposed to have things like parting
words for parents or friends, or thanks for...
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, 両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 感謝[かんしゃ]:thanks/gratitude
遺言って 両親や友達に
別れの言葉とか 感謝の…
（ハチマキ）ねえよ 別に
I don't have anything
to say.
別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, 最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments
あるでしょ？ お別れなんですよ
最後なんですよ？
Of course you do!
You're saying goodbye!
You're dead!
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, おしまい:the end/closing|That's it
いいんだよ 何だって
死んだら 全部おしまいなんだから
It doesn't matter what I write.
Once I'm dead, it's all over for me.
That's the coldest thing I've ever heard!
寂しい[さびしい, さみしい]:lonely/lonesome/solitary
何 寂しいこと
言っちゃってるんですか
If they saw a will like this, the people you
leave behind would break down in tears!
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 悲しむ[かなしむ]:to be sad/to mourn for/to regret
この遺言状 見たら
残された人が悲しみますよ？
You think so? I kinda think
they'd bust out laughing.
笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
そうかなあ 笑うと思うがなあ
This is no good!
Rewrite it!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, 書き直し[かきなおし]:rewriting/rewrite/fair copy
駄目です 書き直し！
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
ったく… なんで お前に―
Unbelievable... What did I ever do to deserve
being lectured by the likes of you?
そんなこと言われなくちゃ
ならねえんだよ
（タナベ）うっ…
（ハチマキ）フンッ！
ほら これでいいだろ？
Here.
Happy now?
うっ…
もう いいです
Oh, forget it.
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 実感[じっかん]:real feeling/actual feeling|to actually feel, 湧く[わく]:to well (up)|to appear (esp. suddenly) (sweat, tears, etc.)|to feel emotions form (joy, bravery, etc.)|
（ヴァンリ）遺言状って言われても
正直 実感 湧かないなあ
All this stuff about last wills just isn't
hitting home for me, to tell you the truth.
It's not like we go out
into space all that often.
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
（シャポウ）私たちは そんなに
宇宙に出るわけじゃないしね
But my section does go out,
so it makes me think...
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, 外[そと, と]:outside|open air|other place, 外[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
でもさ うちは
直接 外に出るから考えちゃうよ
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（リュシー）
他のデブリ課の人たちは―
What are the other Debris Section
people writing in theirs?
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
何て書いてるの？
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
ほら 例のおむつ男とか
Like that diaper guy,
for instance.
落書き[らくがき]:scrawl/scribble/graffiti
（タナベ）ああ 落書き男
Oh, Sketch Boy,
you mean...
落書き[らくがき]:scrawl/scribble/graffiti
落書き？
Sketch Boy?
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 落書き[らくがき]:scrawl/scribble/graffiti, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
だって
遺言状に落書き 書いてあんのよ
The jerk drew a sketch
as his last will!
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
普通は 大事な人に―
Don't you normally write down heartfelt words
for the people who were important to you?
こもる:to shut oneself in (e.g. one's room)/to be confined in|to be filled with (emotion, enthusiasm, etc.), 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
心のこもった言葉を
残すもんじゃない？
うーん:hmm/well, 遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, 個人[こじん]:individual/private person/personal, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you
うーん 遺言なんて
結局 個人の自由でしょ
Well, in the end, a last will
is a personal thing.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
でも 私は嫌だな
I still don't think
it's right.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛だね これは
It must be love.
（タナベたち）はあ？
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy
気になるんでしょ？
その人のこと
That person is on
your mind a lot, isn't he?
色恋[いろこい]:sensual love/love affair, 結び付ける[むすびつける]:to combine/to join/to tie on
リュシーって どうして そう
色恋に結び付けようとするかな
Lucie, why are you trying
to turn this into a love affair?
男女[だんじょ, なんにょ]:men and women/man and woman/both sexes, 男女[おとこおんな]:masculine woman|feminine man|intersexual, 友情[ゆうじょう]:friendship/fellowship/camaraderie, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
私は 男女の友情って
信じないほうだから
Because I don't believe that
men and women can be "just friends."
And what about all those
insurance salesmen, huh?
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
それより 保険屋よ 保険屋
Yeah, that's right! I got suckered
into a married couple's plan!
なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そうそう 私なんて―
夫婦[ふうふ, めおと]:married couple/spouses|his and hers, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, プラン:plan, 入[いり]:entering|setting (of the sun)|containing||, 入[しお]:counter for soakings (of fabric in a dye)
ご夫婦安心プランに
入らされちゃって
結婚[けっこん]:marriage, 同僚[どうりょう]:coworker/co-worker/colleague, 勘弁[かんべん]:pardon/forgiveness/forbearance
（シャポウ）結婚するの？
（ヴァンリ）しないよ 同僚は勘弁
You're getting married?
No, I'm not!
I don't date coworkers.
I dunno, I might.
（リュシー）私はしてもいいな
Who, that pilot?
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, パイロット:pilot
（ヴァンリ）例のパイロット？
（リュシー）そう チェンシンさん
Yeah, Cheng-Shin-san!
（ヴァンリ）ウ～
（リュシー）ウフフッ
That's the last of our interior
maintenance work, right?
内部[ないぶ]:interior/inside/internal, 整備[せいび]:maintenance/servicing|putting in place, おしまい:the end/closing|That's it
（ユーリ）内部整備は
これで おしまいですよね
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, インコ:true parrot (esp. small parrots such as the parakeet, lory and conure)
（ババイヤン）ああ… ああ それと
課長のインコなんだけどさ―
Yep. Oh, and about my chief's parakeet...
Could I leave him with you again?
預かる[あずかる]:to look after|to take charge of|to reserve (judgment), もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
また 預かってもらえねえか？
You mean MacEnroe?
Sure, no problem.
（ユーリ）
マッケンローですね いいですよ
Sorry to keep pushing him
off on you.
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
（ババイヤン）いつも悪いな
（フィー）ユーリ
Yuri.
Yes?
（ユーリ）はい
やっぱり:too/also|still, 台[だい]:stand|support|counter for machines, incl. vehicles||, 台[うてな]:tower|stand|calyx, フィッシュ:fish, ボーン:born
やっぱり もう１台
フィッシュボーンを出すわ
I'm gonna go ahead and send out a second
Fishbone. There's just too much debris.
数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
数が多すぎる
（ババイヤン）じゃ
（ユーリ）分かりました
See you.
I understand. Miss Tanabe probably can't
handle one yet, so I'll take it out.
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
まだ タナベさんには
無理でしょうから 私が出ます
Thanks,
that's a big help.
助かる[たすかる]:to be saved|to escape harm|to be helped, 当[とう]:this (business organisation or place), 当[はた]:or|furthermore|perhaps||
（フィー）
助かるわ …で 当のタナベは―
So, is our little Tanabe
still writing her last will?
書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
まだ書いてるの？ 遺言状
随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
ええ 随分 悩んでいるみたいですよ
Yes, she seems to be
agonizing over it.
アドバイス:advice
アドバイスしましょうか
Shall I offer her
some advice?
放る[ほうる, ほる]:to throw|to throw away|to neglect, 放る[ひる]:to expel (from the body)/to excrete/to defecate
放っといていいよ
No, leave her be.
大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
大事なのは
何を書くかじゃなくて―
What's important isn't
what she writes, but that she learns that this
is a job that might get her killed.
しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
死ぬかもしれない仕事だって
知っとくことだからね
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
（タナベ）
先輩 遺言状のことなんですけど
Senpai, about our last wills...
悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled, 勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|
まだ悩んでるわけ？ お前
ああいうのは勢いだよ
What, you're still racking your brain over that?
Go with your gut with this stuff.
You gotta clear your head and start writing.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
何も考えずに
ガーッと書いちまわねえと
（タナベ）
そんなわけにはいきませんよ
I can't do that.
両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
両親や友達に何を残すのか
残せるのかって考えたら
When I start thinking about what I'll leave to my
parents and friends, or what I should leave, I...
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
（ハチマキ）残すってよ
Leave behind, huh?
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, やっぱり:too/also|still, お金[おかね]:money
（女性）残ってほしいのは
やっぱり お金… でしょ？
What they want you to leave
them is money. Am I right?
Hey, you're...
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill
（タナベ）あっ さっきの…
（ハチマキ）またか
Not again...
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
どう？ 考えてくれた？
So, have you thought
it over?
いーや
I'll pass.
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
彼女の言うとおり―
Like she said just now, deciding what to leave
your loved ones is a difficult question, isn't it?
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 難しい[むずかしい, むつかしい]:difficult|fussy|gloomy||, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
大切な人に何を残すかって
難しい問題よね
But with money they can convert it into all sorts of things, such as goods, but also
medical treatment or an education.
お金[おかね]:money, 品物[しなもの]:goods/article/thing, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 医療[いりょう]:medical care/medical treatment, 教育[きょういく]:training/education, 等[など]:et cetera|or something|the likes of, 等[とう]:class|et cetera|equal
でも お金なら
品物は もちろん医療や教育等―
さまざま:varied/various, 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin, 変える[かえる]:to change/to alter|to reform, ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
さまざまなものに
形を変えることができるわ
Um... I guess.
あっ いや まあ…
What will make a person happy
varies from person to person, right?
幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 感じる[かんじる]:to feel/to sense/to experience, それぞれ:each/respectively
何に幸せを感じるかは
人それぞれよね
So don't you think the best thing is to leave it
up to the person who's going to use it?
使い道[つかいみち]:purpose/utility|way to use something, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
使い道は使う人に任せるのが
一番だと思わない？
ま… まあな
Um... Sure.
That's not right at all!
そんなの違います！
You think so?
かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
そうかしら？
Personally, I think
it's better than giving someone something they don't want and having it go to waste.
望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 無駄[むだ]:futility/uselessness/pointlessness
その人が望んでいないものを残して
無駄になるよりいいと思うけど
This isn't a question of
gaining or losing things!
損[そん]:loss/damage|disadvantage, 得[とく]:profit/advantage|rebirth in paradise, entering nirvana, 得[う]:to get/to acquire|to be possible, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
損とか得とかの話じゃありません！
最後[さいご]:last|no sooner than|one's final moments, 残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left, お金[おかね]:money, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, さみしい:lonely/lonesome/solitary, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
最後に残るのが お金なんて
さみしすぎるって言ってるんです
I'm saying that leaving money behind
when you die is too sad for words!
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
あら そう じゃあ あなたは
大切な人に何を残すつもり？
Oh, you think so? What do you plan
on leaving to your loved ones, then?
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
愛です！
I'll leave them love!
あっ？
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（ハチマキ）愛？
Love...?
Hey! That's it!
I should leave behind love!
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
（タナベ）そうか そうですよ
愛を残せばいいんです！
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
保険も愛でいいじゃないですか
Love is insurance
enough, too!
考え方[かんがえかた]:way of thinking, それぞれ:each/respectively
さあ まあ
考え方は人それぞれだし…
I see.
Well, to each his own, I suppose.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
また来るね 八郎太さん
考えといてねん
I'll see you again, Hachirota-san.
Think it over, okay?
ボーナス:bonus
ボーナス 出たらな
Maybe if I get
a bonus.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（タナベ）そうか 愛だったんだ
That's it... Love was the
answer all along...
意味[いみ]:meaning/significance, すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
お前って ある意味すげえな
Y'know, in a sense,
you're amazing.
はい？
What?
Or at least unpretentious.
天然[てんねん]:nature/spontaneity|natural airhead, 感心[かんしん]:admiration|admirable|astonishment, ほんと:truth/reality|proper
いや 天然つうか
感心したよ ほんと
I was impressed, I have to tell you.
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear, 残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save, 大物[おおもの]:important person/big-shot|big game (animal, fish)
（チェンシン）アハハッ
愛を残すか 大物だね 彼女
She'll leave love, huh?
That girl is a real find.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
一緒に仕事してないから
笑ってられるんだよ
You're only laughing 'cause you
don't have to work with her.
That girl is
seriously scary.
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
実際 怖いぜ あの女
とおり:avenue/street|coming and going, とおり:penetration (as of light)
でも 彼女の言うとおり―
I think she's right, though. You should put some
thought into it when you're writing your will.
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
遺言は
ちゃんと書いたほうがいいと思うよ
でもさ なんか違うんだよな
Maybe, but I sorta think
they're both wrong.
うん？
Money or words or whatever,
that's not what I want to leave when I'm gone.
金[おうごん, こがね]:gold, 金[かね, かな]:money|metal, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech
金とか 言葉とかさ
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
残したいものって
そうじゃねえんだよ
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
じゃあ 何 残すんだって
聞かれたら―
But when somebody asks me what I'm gonna
leave behind, I don't have an answer...
分かんねえけどよ
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one, 業界[ぎょうかい]:business world/business circles/(the) industry, ナンバーワン:number one
（保険外交員１）ご安心ください
うちは業界ナンバーワンですから
Rest assured, sir! We're rated
number one in the industry!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself, ノルマ:(one's) quota/assignment, こなす:to digest|to break down/to break to pieces
（保険外交員２）お願いしますよ
今日中にノルマをこなさないと
I'm begging you! If I don't meet
my quota this month, they'll... Chief?
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
課長さん 課長さーん
Chief!
我慢[がまん]:patience/endurance/perseverance, 時期[じき]:time/season|soon, 乗り切る[のりきる]:to weather (a storm, rough seas)|to get through (adversity)|to load completely (e.g. books on a shelf, people or luggage in a car)
（課長）我慢 我慢
この時期さえ乗り切れば
Hang in there... Hang in there... I just need
to make it through this one last season.
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief
（ラビィ）課長
Remember, Chief, I was the one
who came up with this nice little plan.
ナイス:nice, 作戦[さくせん]:tactics/strategy|military or naval operations, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
このナイスな作戦を考えたのは
私ですからね
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
（エーデル）課長補佐
Chief, this paperwork
is all right, isn't it?
書類[しょるい]:documents/official papers
この書類は
これでいいんですよね？
余計[よけい]:too many|unnecessary|abundantly, 保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee
（課長）これで
余計な保険に入ることもない
This way, I won't sign up for
insurance that I don't need!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance, 定年退職[ていねんたいしょく]:(compulsory) retirement (e.g. on reaching the age of 60)/mandatory retirement/reaching retirement age
（エーデル）課長補佐
（ラビィ）定年退職したとき―
Chief?
Recommend me as your replacement
once you retire, okay?
後釜[あとがま]:successor/replacement|second wife, 推薦[すいせん]:recommendation/referral/endorsement, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
後釜には
このラビィを推薦してくださいよ
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
（エーデル）
係長補佐でもいいんですけど
You can check this, too, Manager.
働く[はたらく]:to work|to function|to commit (e.g. a crime)|
（エーデル）働けよ
Do some work,
damn it...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
（タナベ）先輩
遺言状のことなんですけど
Senpai, about that will...
（ハチマキ）
ああっ お前もしつけえなあ
Crap, you're persistent!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）先輩の分ですって
I mean yours!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
私 考えたんですけど―
I've been thinking, and, well,
does a last will have to be words?
遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 文字[もじ, もんじ]:letter (of alphabet)/character|literal
遺言状って 文字じゃなくても
いいんじゃないですか？
あっ…
Why do you think I drew a picture?
絵を描く[えをかく, えをえがく]:to paint (draw) a picture
（ハチマキ）
だから 絵を描いたじゃないか
No, what about a movie letter
or something?
ムービー:movie, レター:letter
（タナベ）そうじゃなくて
ムービーレターとか どうですか？
文字[もじ, もんじ]:letter (of alphabet)/character|literal, 構える[かまえる]:to set up (a house, store, etc.)|to have at the ready (e.g. a gun)|to adopt a posture||, ムービー:movie
文字だと構えちゃうけど
ムービーだったら―
With words, you sound formal,
but with a movie letter,
...you could be lighthearted about it,
like you were calling your mom or dad.
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, お母さん[おかあさん]:mother, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, 気軽[きがる]:carefree/buoyant|ease
お父さんやお母さんに
電話する気分で 気軽に…
I can't do that!
I can't call my old man!
親父[おやじ, ろうや]:one's father/old man/one's boss, 電話[でんわ]:telephone call/phone call|telephone (device), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（ハチマキ）できるわけねえだろ！
親父(おやじ)に電話なんて
（タナベ）えっ あっ…
すいません 私 知らなくて
I'm sorry, I didn't know...
Nah, he's alive.
Alive, kicking, and then some.
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
（ハチマキ）
生きてるって ピンピンしてるよ
Did you have a falling out? Shouldn't you have
outgrown your rebellious phase by now?
仲[なか]:relation/relationship, 仲[すあい, すわい]:broker/brokerage/brokerage fee, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 反抗期[はんこうき]:rebellious age
（タナベ）仲 悪いんですか？
反抗期にしても長すぎでしょ？
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
お父さんに心配かけちゃ…
（ハチマキ）うるせえ！
You shouldn't make
your father worry...
Shut up!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 口出し[くちだし]:interference/meddling/butting in
ただの仕事仲間が
家(うち)の中まで口出しすんな！
A stupid coworker doesn't have any right
to butt into my family life!
うっとうしい:gloomy (e.g. mood)/depressing|irritating, いちいち:one-by-one/separately|every single
うっとうしいんだよ
いちいち お前は
You're getting on my damn nerves
with all your nagging!
（タナベ）あっ…
やっぱり:too/also|still, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
（ハチマキ）ユーリ やっぱり
手伝ってもらって よかったよ
Yuri, I'm glad we had you
come out here to help.
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
新人と２人でやるには多すぎる
There's too much to handle
with just me and the rookie.
残業[ざんぎょう]:overtime (work), もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me)
（フィー）みんな
ちょっと 残業してもらえる？
Guys, could I talk you
into some overtime?
急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, デブリ:debris
急で悪いんだけど
拾ってもらいたいデブリがあるの
Sorry for the short notice, but there's a piece
of debris that I want you to pick up.
短[たん]:fault/defect|minor, 短[みじか]:short/brief, 周期[しゅうき]:cycle/period, すい星[すいせい]:comet, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
短周期のすい星軌道を
飛んでたやつが―
Looks like something that was on a short-period cometary orbit got grabbed by Earth's gravity.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 引力[いんりょく]:attraction (e.g. magnetic, gravitation)/affinity|attractiveness, つかまる:to be caught/to be arrested|to hold on to, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
地球の引力に
つかまっちゃったらしいのよ
I bet it's just scrap metal
or something, but still...
鉄くず[てつくず]:scrap iron
まあ 鉄くずか何かだと思うけど
いっぱい:one defeat, いっぱい:amount necessary to fill a container (e.g. cupful, spoonful, etc.)/drink (usu. alcoholic)|full, 拾う[ひろう]:to pick up/to find/to gather
（ハチマキ）俺たち
いっぱい拾ったとこなんだけど
We've already got a pretty
big haul as it is...
They say there's a research agency that wants it.
Plus, you're already in the neighborhood.
欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation, 機関[からくり]:mechanism|trick|mechanical doll, 機関[きかん]:engine|agency|system
欲しがってる
研究機関があるんだって
近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
あんたたちのすぐ近くだから
（ハチマキ）えーっ
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
文句 言わない研究には…
Save the complaints.
It's for research, so...
文句[もんく]:complaint/grumbling|phrase, 研究[けんきゅう]:study/research/investigation
文句 言わない研究には…
うん？ 何？ これ
What is that?
Preparedness is peace of mind!
Satisfaction once you're signed up!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 備える[そなえる]:to furnish|to have ready|to possess (all that is needed)|, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 満足[まんぞく]:satisfaction/contentment|sufficient
（保険外交員１）
備えて安心 入って満足
Accidents are covered, of course,
as are you're family's...
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family
（保険外交員２）
事故はもちろん家族まで
Three months, that's all I ask!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, か月[かげつ]:months (period of)
（保険外交員３）
３か月だけでいいから！
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 業界[ぎょうかい]:business world/business circles/(the) industry, ナンバーワン:number one
（保険外交員４）
業界ナンバーワン！
We're rated number one in the industry!
Our company offers
300% peace of mind!
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, パーセント:percent/percentage, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company
（保険外交員５）
安心 300パーセント 我が社に
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, 目を通す[めをとおす]:to scan/to look over, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
（保険外交員６）どうでしょう
目を通していただくだけでも
Please, just look it over...
保険[ほけん]:insurance/guarantee, 外交員[がいこういん]:canvasser/door-to-door salesman, お嬢[おじょう]:(someone else's) daughter, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
（保険外交員７）
お嬢さん どこか決められました？
Hello there, Miss! Have you settled
on an insurance company yet?
派遣社員[はけんしゃいん]:temporary employee (esp. from an agency)/temporary worker/agency temp
私は派遣社員ですので
No, I'm a temp worker.
そうですか
Oh, is that so? Well, I'll leave a
pamphlet on the desk just in case.
机[つくえ, つき]:desk, パンフ:pamphlet, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||
じゃ 机の上に
パンフだけ置いておきますね
要る[いる]:to need/to want, っつう:meaning/called/said
要らないっつうの
I don't need any, you jerk.
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 一足[いっそく]:pair (footwear), 一足[ひとあし]:step|short distance/short time, 先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 避難[ひなん]:taking refuge/finding shelter/evacuation
申し訳ありません 課長
私は 一足先に避難させて…
I'm sorry, Chief, but I'm
abandoning ship...
あっ…
いかが:how/in what way/how about, お子さん[おこさん]:child, 将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
（女性）いかがでしょう
お子さんの将来も考えてみては
How about it? Shouldn't you
think of your children's future?
Our tuition plan was put together
with exactly that in mind!
用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision, 我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 学費[がくひ]:tuition/school expenses, プラン:plan, 得[とく]:profit/advantage|rebirth in paradise, entering nirvana, 得[う]:to get/to acquire|to be possible
そのためだけに用意された
我が社の学費プラン お得ですよ
It's a bargain.
まったく:really/truly|indeed
もう 何言うのよ まったく
How many of you people
are there?
やっぱり:too/also|still
やっぱりか
Just as I thought...
（タナベ）何なんですか？ それ
What is that thing?
Take a look.
（ハチマキ）ほらよ
えっ…
えっ うわっ そ… それは！
I-lt's a...
おいおい:Hey!/Wait a minute!|boohoo, おいおい:gradually/by degrees/little by little, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 面[おもて, おも]:face|surface|mask (esp. a noh or kyogen mask), 面[つら]:face|surface|surrounding area|, 笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
おいおい なんて面だい
笑ってやんの
Holy crap, would you look
at that expression?
He's smiling.
Is that seriously a...
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance
（タナベ）それって もしかして…
A coffin from
a space burial.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 棺おけ[かんおけ]:coffin/casket, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
宇宙葬の棺おけですよ
ここに書いてあります
It's written right here.
"Astronaut lbn Fadlan."
航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 士[さむらい, さぶらい]:warrior (esp. of military retainers of daimyos in the Edo period)/samurai|man in attendance (on a person of high standing), 士[し]:man (esp. one who is well-respected)|samurai|person (in a certain profession, esp. licensed)
“航宙士 イブン･ファドラン”
"In accordance with his final wishes,
he set sail into the infinite sea. 2024."
遺言[ゆいごん, いごん]:will/testament/last request, 無限[むげん]:infinity/infinitude|infinite, 海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, 船出[ふなで]:setting sail/putting out to sea
“遺言により
無限の海に船出す 2024年”
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 廃止[はいし]:abolition/repeal, 直前[ちょくぜん]:just before
宇宙葬 廃止直前ですね
That was right before space
burials were banned.
It's a corpse from
more than 50 years ago.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 仏[ふつ]:France, 仏[ぶつ]:Buddha/Buddhism
50年以上前の仏さんだ
He must've been launched on a heading
to leave the solar system,
太陽[たいよう]:sun/solar, 向ける[むける]:to turn towards/to point, 射る[いる]:to shoot (arrow, bolt, dart), 出す[だす]:to take out|to put out|to submit (e.g. thesis)||
太陽系外に向けて
射出されたんだろうが―
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
戻ってきちまったんだな
...but it looks like
he came back.
はあ…
He must've wanted to reach
the edge of the universe,
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 果て[はて]:the end/the extremity/the limit
（ハチマキ）宇宙の果てまで
行きたかったんだろうが―
重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 振り切る[ふりきる]:to shake off/to shake free from|to swing completely
重力を振り切れなかったんだ
...but he couldn't
break free of gravity.
The odds against this are incredible.
It's damn near a miracle.
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable, 確率[かくりつ]:probability/likelihood/chances, ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically, 奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel
でも すげえ確率
ほとんど奇跡だよ
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, ランデブー:meeting/rendez-vous
あの軌道じゃ
次に地球とランデブーするのは―
On that orbit, his next rendezvous with Earth
wouldn't have been for another 700 years.
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
700年後だもんな
What's going to be done
with the body?
遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains
あの遺体 どうなるんですか？
Don't know, don't care.
知らねえよ そんなの
Our job's to collect debris,
end of story.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
俺たちの仕事は
デブリを回収するだけだしさ
What do you mean, debris?
That's a person's body!
デブリ:debris, 遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains
デブリって 遺体ですよ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, 不必要[ふひつよう]:unnecessary/needless, 物体[ぶったい]:body/object, 物体[もったい]:superior airs/air of importance|overemphasis, デブリ:debris, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
宇宙に浮かんでる不必要な物体は
デブリに決まってるだろ？
Any useless object floating around
in space is debris, you know?
How can you be
so coldhearted?
さみしい:lonely/lonesome/solitary, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）
さみしいこと 言わないでください
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 証し[しるし]:mark|symbol|badge||, 証し[あかし, しょう]:proof (e.g. of love, of innocence)|license|to testify (usu. Christian religious context)
あれは人の生きてきた証しです！
（ハチマキ）うっ… わあっ
It's proof that he
was alive once!
信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in, 物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 扱い[あつかい]:treatment/service, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
信じられない 物扱いするなんて
You're unbelievable,
treating that man like a thing!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 何回[なんかい]:how many times?
お前な 仕事だって
何回 言ったら分かるんだよ
How many times am I gonna have to spell out
your job description before it sinks in?
ご苦労[ごくろう]:trouble (I have put you through)
ご苦労さん みんな
Good work, everyone.
フィー:phi, 遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains
フィーさん
あの遺体 どうなるんですか？
Fee-san, what's gonna happen
to that body?
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 遺族[いぞく]:bereaved family, 連絡を取る[れんらくをとる]:to get in touch with
今 管制課が
遺族と連絡を取ってる
Control Section is contacting
his next of kin as we speak.
法律上[ほうりつじょう]:legal, 遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains, 所有権[しょゆうけん]:ownership/dominion/ownership rights, 遺族[いぞく]:bereaved family
法律上 遺体の所有権は
遺族にあるんだって
They said that legally speaking, the body
is the property of the next of kin.
This is Seven Delivery.
You are cleared for flight to Baikonur...
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), セブン:seven, デリバリー:delivery
（管制官）
こちら セブンデリバリー…
You're certain that
it's my father?
（ファドランの娘）
本当に父なんですか？
大変[たいへん]:very|immense|serious||, 珍しい[めずらしい]:unusual|new|fine (e.g. gift), ケース:case (e.g. receptacle, condition, event, legal action, letter style, etc.)
（クレア）
ええ 大変 珍しいケースです
Yes, ma'am. This is
a most unusual case.
As far as burials conducted
prior to 2028 are concerned,
以前[いぜん]:ago/since/before, 行う[おこなう]:to perform/to do/to conduct oneself, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related
2028年以前に行われた
宇宙葬に関しては―
...you would be able to re-bury him
as a special exception.
特例[とくれい]:special case/exception, やり直し[やりなおし]:redoing
特例として
やり直しもできますが？
（ファドランの娘）あの…
Um...
（クレア）はい
Ma'am?
回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 話せる[はなせる]:to be able to speak/to be able to talk|to be understanding
回収された方と話せますか？
Would it be possible for me to speak
with the people who recovered him?
航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 士[さむらい, さぶらい]:warrior (esp. of military retainers of daimyos in the Edo period)/samurai|man in attendance (on a person of high standing), 士[し]:man (esp. one who is well-respected)|samurai|person (in a certain profession, esp. licensed), 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman)
ファドラン航宙士の娘さん？
Astronaut Fadlan's daughter?
直接[ちょくせつ]:direct/immediate/personal, そちら:that way (direction distant from the speaker, close to the listener)|there (place distant from the speaker, close to the listener), 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（クレア）ええ 直接 そちらと
話したいということなので―
Yes. She says she'd like to speak with you face
to face, so I'm going to patch her through.
回線[かいせん]:circuit/line, つなぐ:to connect/to link together|to tie, つなぐ:rigging, コピー:copy/photocopy
回線をつなぎます ユ ーコピー？
コピー:copy/photocopy
（フィー）アイ コピー
You copy?
I copy.
航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 士[さむらい, さぶらい]:warrior (esp. of military retainers of daimyos in the Edo period)/samurai|man in attendance (on a person of high standing), 士[し]:man (esp. one who is well-respected)|samurai|person (in a certain profession, esp. licensed), 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
ファドラン航宙士を回収した
DS-12の船長―
I'm Fee Carmichael, captain of the DS-12, the
ship that recovered Astronaut Fadlan's body.
フィー:phi
フィー･カーマイケルです
Um... This is an awkward question,
but how did my father's body look?
その…
つかぬことをお聞きしますが―
遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 様子[ようす]:state|appearance|sign
父の遺体は どんな様子でした？
（フィー）え？
I'm ashamed to say it, but I
never looked at my father's body.
恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful, ながら:while/during|while
（ファドランの娘）
恥ずかしながら―
遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
私 父の遺体を
確認していないんです
ああ…
He was smiling.
He must've had a full life.
笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|, 仏[ふつ]:France, 仏[ぶつ]:Buddha/Buddhism, 満足[まんぞく]:satisfaction/contentment|sufficient, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
笑ってたよ 仏さん
満足な人生だったんだろうな
あっ…
そうですか
I see.
あの… 何か？
Is something
the matter?
純粋[じゅんすい]:pure/true/genuine, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（ファドランの娘）父は…
私の父は純粋な宇宙飛行士でした
Father... My father was an astronaut
through and through.
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), プレーン:plain, パイロット:pilot, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
スペースプレーンの
パイロットという仕事を―
He was extremely proud of his work
as the pilot of a spaceplane,
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 誇り[ほこり]:pride/boast, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
とても誇りにしていて―
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰ってくる[かえってくる]:to return/to come back
私たちが待っている
家に帰ってくることは―
...and he seldom returned to the home
where we were waiting for him.
ほとんど:mostly/nearly/practically
ほとんどなく…
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 放射線[ほうしゃせん]:radiation, 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing
しかし 宇宙放射線で
体を悪くし―
But he grew sick
from cosmic radiation,
引退[いんたい]:retire, 間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 息を引き取る[いきをひきとる]:to pass away/to breathe one's last
引退して間もなく
息を引き取りました
...and soon after he retired,
he passed away.
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 言い残す[いいのこす]:to leave word with (a person)/to state in one's will/to leave (something) unsaid
“地球で死にたくない”と
言い残して…
He stated in his will that he
didn't want to be buried on Earth.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
私 怖かったんですね
父の顔を見るのが
I suppose I was afraid
to look at my father's face.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.), 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
宇宙葬をしてしまったら
もう 本当に会えなくなるのに―
I knew that once we held the space burial,
I would never be able to see him again,
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
どんな顔しているんだろうと
考えたら…
...but when I wondered to myself what sort
of expression he had on his face, I...
現に[げんに]:actually/really, 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament
現に 遺言状に―
The truth is, my mother and I were not
mentioned at all in his will.
母[はは, はわ]:mother, ひと言[ひとこと, いちげん]:single word/a few words/brief comment, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
私と母のことなど
ひと言も書かれていませんでしたし
遠い[とおい]:far/distant
いつも遠い目をしている人で―
He was a man whose eyes
were always on the horizon,
焦点[しょうてん]:focus (e.g. photographic)/focal point, 通り越す[とおりこす]:to go past (a place or thing)/to go beyond
私を見ていても
目の焦点は私を通り越していました
...and even when he did look at me, they were
always focused on a point far beyond me.
焦点[しょうてん]:focus (e.g. photographic)/focal point, 深[み]:august|beautiful, 深[ふけ]:growing late/latening, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 結ぶ[むすぶ]:to tie|to bear (fruit)|to close (e.g. deal)||
父の目の焦点は いつも
深宇宙で結ばれていたのです
Father's eyes were always
locked on deep space.
Is that true...?
So, Father was smiling, was he?
笑う[わらう]:to laugh|to smile|to sneer|
そうですか
笑っていましたか 父は
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
父は…
父を宇宙に返してやってください
Father... Please send Father
back into space.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, やり直す[やりなおす]:to do over again/to redo/to start over
分かりました では こちらで
宇宙葬をやり直します
I understand. In that case,
we'll see to re-burying him ourselves.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
よろしく お願いします
Thank you for all
your trouble.
本望[ほんもう]:long-cherished ambition/satisfaction
それが父の本望でしょうから
I think this is what my father
would have wanted.
No, you can't do that!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
駄目ですよ そんなの
何言っちゃってるんですか？
What are you saying?!
落ち着く[おちつく]:to calm down|to calm down|to settle down (in a location, job, etc.)||, なさる:to do
（フィー）ちょ…
落ち着きなさい タナベ
Calm down, Tanabe!
You can't send your father
back into space!
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
お父さんを
宇宙に返しちゃいけません
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
家族なら一緒にいなくちゃ
You're his family,
so he should be with you!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 昨日今日[きのうきょう]:yesterday and today|(something that happened) only yesterday (just recently), 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, ばっか:only/merely|approximately
おい 新入り
昨日今日 宇宙に出たばっかで―
Hey, rookie, you haven't been in space that long,
so don't start talking like you own the place!
勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, 抜かす[ぬかす]:to omit/to leave out|to say
勝手なこと抜かしてんじゃ…
んんん…
お父さん[おとうさん, おとっさん]:father/dad/papa, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect)
お父さんは大事でしょう？
Your father's precious to you,
isn't he?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
そんなの宇宙だろうが
地球だろうが 一緒です！
Whether he's in Earth or space,
that doesn't change!
タナベ！
Tanabe!
Aw, just let
that little twerp go.
放る[ほうる, ほる]:to throw|to throw away|to neglect, 放る[ひる]:to expel (from the body)/to excrete/to defecate, あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25)
放っとけ あんなやつ
What she says does make
some sense, though.
一理[いちり]:(a) principle/(a) reason/(a) point
しかし
彼女の言うことにも一理ある
ああ？
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation)
（タナベ）ったく もう…
Unbelievable... What is it with astronauts
and trying to act tough?!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, ばっかり:only/merely|approximately
宇宙飛行士ってやつは
カッコばっかりつけて
当社[とうしゃ]:(this) shrine|(this) company/(this) firm, 搬送[はんそう]:transportation/conveyance|hospitalization
では 当社で搬送し―
All right, then. Our company
will ship him to the moon,
月面[げつめん]:moon's surface, マスドライバー:mass driver/electromagnetic catapult, 太陽[たいよう]:sun/solar, 射る[いる]:to shoot (arrow, bolt, dart), 出す[だす]:to take out|to put out|to submit (e.g. thesis)||
月面上のマスドライバーで
太陽系外へ射出します
...where we'll fire him towards extra-solar space
using the mass driver there.
よろしい:good/OK/all right
よろしいですね？
Is that all right?
結構[けっこう]:splendid|sufficient|well enough||
はい それで結構です
Yes, that's fine.
（フィー）分かりました
Very well, then.
墓場[はかば]:graveyard/cemetery, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
ハチ 墓場軌道に向かうよ
Hachi, we're heading for the graveyard orbit.
Pass word to Tanabe.
伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
タナベにも伝えて
（ハチマキ）ああ
Sure. Hey, rookie! How long
are you gonna keep sulking?
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
おい 新入り
すねる:to be peevish/to sulk/to pout
いつまで すねてんだよ
（フィー）ん？
ああっ！
（ハチマキ）どうした？
What's wrong?
コンテナ:container (e.g. shipping)/skip
あのバカ コンテナを
That little idiot opened
the cargo container!
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）
何 考えてんだ？ 新入りのやつ
What the hell
is that rookie thinking?
いっぺん:complete change/about-face, いっぺん:(a) slice/(a) piece, 締める[しめる]:to tie|to wear (necktie, belt)|to total||
いっぺん 締めて―
We're gonna have to wring her neck
to let her know who's boss around here.
上下[うえした]:top and bottom/up and down|upside-down, 上下[じょうげ]:top and bottom|going up and down|going and coming back||, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
上下関係ってもんを
教えてやらねえとな
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, なさる:to do
（フィー）タナベ
戻ってきなさい タナベ
Tanabe, come back! Tanabe!
Damn it, girl,
answer me!
返事[へんじ]:reply/answer/response, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
返事ぐらいしろってんだよ！
戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, っつう:meaning/called/said
戻ってこいっつってんだろうが
ああ？
Get your ass back
in here, damn it!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）こら！
何しようとしてんだ？ 新入り
Hey!
What are you trying
to pull, rookie?!
Don't come near me!
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
来ないでください！
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with, 大気圏[たいきけん]:the atmosphere, ぶん投げる[ぶんなげる]:to throw (strongly, violently, etc.)
それ以上 近づくと
大気圏にぶん投げますよ これ
If you come any closer, I'll chuck
this thing into the atmosphere!
（ハチマキ）えっ…
な… 何言ってんだよ おい
W-What are you saying?
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth
本気ですからね
I'm serious!
Um...
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと…
底なし[そこなし]:bottomless/endlessly deep/infinite
お前 バカだ 底なしだ
You're an idiot.
A bottomless pit of stupidity.
意味がある[いみがある]:to have meaning/to be meaningful
そんなことに
何の意味があんだよ
What good is that
gonna do?
Look at that will you wrote!
You're the one with the problem!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
先輩なんて―
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 遺言状[ゆいごんじょう]:will/testament, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
あんな遺言状 書いてるから
いけないんですよ
どうして 分からないんですか？
Why can't you understand?!
We can't send this man back into space!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
この人は
宇宙に返しちゃ駄目なんです！
決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
（ハチマキ）そんなの
お前が決めることじゃねえだろ
That's not up to you
to decide!
That man wanted
to be buried in space!
仏[ふつ]:France, 仏[ぶつ]:Buddha/Buddhism, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
その仏さんは
宇宙で死にたかったんだ
As a fellow astronaut,
I understand how he feels.
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
同じ宇宙飛行士として
その気持ちは分かる
そうさせてやろうぜ
Let's give him
what he wants!
後悔[こうかい]:regret/repentance/remorse
違います！
ファドランさんは後悔してたんです
You're wrong! Mr. Fadlan
regretted his decision!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, さまよう:to loiter/to putter/to prowl, やっぱり:too/also|still, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
宇宙をさまよって やっぱり
戻ってきたいと思ったんですよ
He was drifting in space and he
said to himself, "I want to go back!"
言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
どうして
そんなことが言えるんだ！
How can you say that?!
Don't ignore the man's wishes
and force your own dreams on him!
本人[ほんにん]:the person himself, 無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring, 自分勝手[じぶんかって, じぶんがって]:selfishness/egotism/egoism, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
本人 無視して
自分勝手な夢 見てんじゃねえよ
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
でも… でも ファドランさんは
帰ってきたんですよ
But Mr. Fadlan came back!
Against astronomical odds!
天文学的[てんもんがくてき]:astronomical, 確率[かくりつ]:probability/likelihood/chances, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel
天文学的な確率で
先輩も奇跡だって
You yourself said
it was a miracle!
奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel
奇跡って お前…
A miracle?
What are you...
And why do you suppose
that miracle happened?
奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel, 起きる[おきる]:to get up|to wake up|to occur (usu. of unfavourable incidents)
（タナベ）どうして
奇跡が起きたんだと思います？
願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
それは ファドランさんが
そう願ったからです
Because Mr. Fadlan
wished for it!
奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel, 起こす[おこす]:to raise|to wake|to cause||, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
奇跡を起こすくらい
強く願ったからです
He wanted it so bad that
it made a miracle happen!
He said, "I want to go back to Earth!
I want to go back to my family!"
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family
地球に戻りたい
家族のところに行きたいって！
偶然[ぐうぜん]:coincidence|by chance|contingency (philosophy)
違う！ ただの偶然だ
You're wrong!
It was just a coincidence!
奇跡[きせき]:miracle/wonder/marvel
（タナベ）奇跡です！
It was a miracle!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 都合[つごう]:circumstances|to arrange|to lend money|, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
先輩こそ 自分に都合よく
言わないでくださいよ
Don't you go saying what
you want to hear, Senpai!
（ハチマキ）なんでだよ
Why are you doing this?! It was his
own choice to live alone and die alone!
一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
そのおっさんは 一人で生きて
一人で死ぬって決めたんだ
And it was
the wrong decision!
絶対[ぜったい]:absolutely|absolute|absoluteness
絶対に違います！
愛す[あいす]:to love
だって ファドランさんは
愛されてるじゃないですか
For one thing, Fadlan-sama is loved by people, isn't he?!
By his wife, his daughter, and I bet
even his parents and friends, too!
奥さん[おくさん]:wife/your wife/his wife, 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 両親[りょうしん, ふたおや]:parents/both parents, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
奥さんや 娘さんや
きっと 両親や友達にも
自分勝手[じぶんかって, じぶんがって]:selfishness/egotism/egoism, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, かなた:beyond/across/the other side
そういう人が自分勝手なことして
宇宙のかなたで―
A man like that can't be selfish and decide to
turn into a mummy at the ends of the universe!
冷凍[れいとう]:freezing/cold storage/refrigeration, ミイラ:mummy, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
冷凍ミイラに
なったりしちゃ駄目です！
地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
地球に戻るべきなんです
それが愛じゃないんですか？
He should go back to Earth!
Isn't that what love's all about?
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 戻る[もどる]:to turn back (e.g. half-way)|to return|to recover (e.g. something lost)|, 戻る[もとる]:to go against/to act contrary to/to deviate from
私なら 死んでも
大切な人のところに戻ってきますよ
If it were me, I'd want to go back and be
with my loved ones, even if I was dead!
Living alone
and dying alone...
生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
１人で生きて １人で死んで
１人で…
Alone...
満足[まんぞく]:satisfaction/contentment|sufficient, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
なんで満足できるんですか？
バカみたい
How could anyone
be satisfied with that?
It's stupid...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
宇宙は
１人きりじゃ広すぎるのに…
Space is too big
to face all alone.
船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
（ファドランの娘）
あの… 船長さん
Um... Captain?
ん？
棺おけ[かんおけ]:coffin/casket, 下ろす[おろす]:to take down (e.g. flag)|to drop off (a passenger from a vehicle)|to withdraw money from an account||, なさる:to do
（フィー）
棺おけ 下ろしなさい タナベ
Put the coffin down, Tanabe. His daughter
says she wants to claim the body.
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), 遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains, 引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place
娘さんが遺体を引き取りたいって
はっ…
くっ…
What?
（タナベ）ええっ…
But I've already sent the forms
over to Welfare Section...
手続き[てつづき]:procedure/(legal) process/formalities, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 福祉[ふくし]:welfare/well-being/social welfare, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
でも 手続きはこちらだって
福祉課に…
はい 分かりました
Yes, sir, I understand.
（ユーリ）どうしたんです？
What's the matter?
遺体[いたい]:corpse/remains, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 下ろす[おろす]:to take down (e.g. flag)|to drop off (a passenger from a vehicle)|to withdraw money from an account||, 手続き[てつづき]:procedure/(legal) process/formalities, いろいろ:various|various colors (colours), 面倒[めんどう]:trouble|trouble|care
遺体を地球に下ろす手続きって
いろいろ面倒なのよ
There's a lot of hoops to jump through
to send a body back to Earth.
あそこ:there (place physically distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|genitals, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
でも あそこまで言ったからには
やってもらわないといけませんね
Still, after all those things she said,
she has to be the one to deal with it.
The written report?
I'm submitting it to INTO, so...
報告書[ほうこくしょ]:(written) report, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 提出[ていしゅつ]:to present/to submit (e.g. a report or a thesis)|presentation
報告書？ 連合に提出するので…
書式[しょしき]:blank form/format
書式が違う？
It's not written properly?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
確か 前のに…
Hang on...
It was around here...
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
うわあ！
契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement, ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ご契約 ありがとうございました
Thank you so much
for the contracts!
母ちゃん[かあちゃん]:mum/mom
（課長）ごめんよ 母ちゃん
Forgive me, Mother...!
教育[きょういく]:training/education, ローン:loan
（ラビィ）教育ローンが…
What do I need with
a student loan?!
あら？
Hm?
契約[けいやく]:contract/compact/agreement, まとまる:to be collected/to be settled/to be in order, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
よう 契約まとまったみたいだな
Hey. Looks like you
got your contracts.
なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
あなたとは まだでしょ？
これなんか どう？
I still haven't got one from you, though.
How about this, then?
It's our top of the line item.
The "Double Plan for Lovers."
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 商品[しょうひん]:commodity/article of commerce/goods, 愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection, ダブル:double, プラン:plan
我が社のイチオシ商品
愛情ダブルプラン
愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
ケッ！ 何が愛だよ
（女性）え？
"Love," my ass...
認める[したためる]:to write up, 認める[みとめる]:to recognize|to deem|to approve||
俺は認めないぞ
I don't buy it.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 甘い[あまい]:sweet-tasting|fragrant (smelling)|lightly salted||, 甘い[うまい]:skillful|delicious|fortunate, たまる:to collect/to gather/to save, たまる:to be saved up (e.g. money)
宇宙がそんなに甘くて
たまるかってんだよ
No way in hell is the universe
that sentimental!
♪～
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
Next Time
Part of the Job
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
その新入りっての―
Could you please stop
with that "rookie" stuff?
かげん:(moon's) last quarter, かげん:lower limit|infimum, やめる:to stop (an activity)/to cease|to cancel, やめる:to resign/to retire/to quit, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
いいかげん
やめてください
コリン:choline
（コリン）
僕 コリン･クリフォード
I'm Colin Clifford.
Maybe you've heard of me.
知ってるかな？
（ハチマキ）あっ…
Why does it have to be us?
Go make the PR Section do it!
なんで俺たちなんだよ
広報[こうほう]:public relations/PR/publicity, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 言える[いえる]:to be possible to say/to be able to say
そういうのは
広報課にでも言えよな
We're doing this
to help you.
あなたたちのために
やってるのよ
ああ？
That way, your parents would never know
that you collect garbage in space.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 拾い[じゅう, とお]:ten, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
宇宙でゴミ拾いなんて―
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), ないしょ:secrecy/confidentiality|one's circumstances (esp. fiscal)
親にも
ないしょだったりして
You do the same pathetic job,
day in and day out.
毎日[まいにち]:every day
毎日 毎日―
くだる:to descend/to go down|to be handed down (of an order, judgment, etc.), 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, ちまちま:small/compact
くだんない仕事を
ちまちまとさ
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||, 最高[さいこう]:most/highest|best, カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure
デブリ屋は
最高にカッコいいです
Debris collectors are
as cool as they come!